A Guide to the Powhatan (Polly) Stone Papers 1920-1976
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Powhatan (Polly) Stone Papers 1920-1976
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 79
12.4 linear feet
Powhatan Stone
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the Department by Miss Stone on July 1, 1976.
Biographical/Historical Information
Powhatan Stone was born in Knoxville, Tennessee on February 26, 1891. Her family soon moved back to their original home in Virginia where Miss Stone attended school. After her mother's death, Polly left school to care for her younger brothers and sisters. In 1913, Stone moved to Washington, D.C. for training in nursing, returning to Richmond for private duty nursing until 1917. At the entry of the U.S. into World War I, Miss Stone joined the McGuire Unit and was sent to France to work in a field hospital for the last four months of the war.
Upon returning home, Stone received training from the Red Cross and became a public health nurse. For the next eight years, she was a public health nurse, first in Kansas and then in Virginia. Her next position took her to the University of Chicago's Billings Hospital. Here, Stone was able to study while working at the hospital until poor health forced her to resign and move back to Virginia. After working for the Department of Health in a variety of positions, Stone attained a job with the State Board of Education. She remained there until her retirement 23 years later.
Possessed of a desire to express herself more creatively in writing, she enrolled in a writing courses at RPI after her retirement.
Scope and Content Information
This collection covers the span of Miss Stone's working life from 1920 onward. The material divides itself into three groups. The first group includes dialogues by Miss Stone about her job and the people, places and things which she encountered. The second group includes correspondence dating from 1920 to 1976. The third group consists of the majority of her literary works including essays, poetry, short stories and class notes.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged into two series, personal and literary papers. The personal collection is arranged topically and then chronologically. The literary papers are sorted alphabetically.
Contents List
- Series I-Personal
  - Nutrition Clinic Certificate 1928 (Box 1)
  - Nursing Materials-Nutrition 1923-1928 (Box 1)
  - Nutrition Notes 1925 (Box 1)
  - Summary of work as public health nurse of Wythe Co., Va (Box 1)
  - Narratives and Tales-S.W. Virginia (Box 1)
  - Dialogues-Tennessee and S.W. Virginia (Box 1)
  - Dialogues 1921 (Box 1)
  - Dialogues 1923 (Box 1)
  - Dialogues 1924 (Box 1)
  - Dialogues 1925 (Box 1)
  - Dialogues 1926 (Box 1)
  - Dialogues 1927 (Box 1)
  - Dialogues 1928 (Box 1)
  - Dialogues 1929 (Box 1)
  - Narratives and Tales-Chicago 1928-1931 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1930 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1931 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1932 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1933 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1934 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1935 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1936 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1937 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1939 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1940 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1944 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1945 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1946 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1947 (Box 2)
  - Dialogues 1948, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Dialogues 1949, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Dialogues 1950 (Box 5)
  - Dialogues 1951 (Box 5)
  - Dialogues 1953 (Box 5)
  - Dialogues 1955 (Box 5)
  - Dialogues 1956 (Box 5)
  - Dialogues 1957, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Dialogues (July-December) 1958 (Box 7)
  - Dialogues 1959 (Box 7)
  - Dialogues 1976 (Box 7)
  - Dialogues, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Notebooks, n.d. (Box 8)
  - Photo of P. Stone in training, Washington, D.C. 1913-1916 (Box 9)
  - Graduation program and invitation-Garfield Memorial Hospital 1916 (Box 9)
  - Red Cross Nursing Certificate 1917 (Box 9)
  - Nurses Examining Board Receipt 1916 (Box 9)
  - WWI Nurses cap, cuff, dog tag and pins 1918 (Box 9)
  - Newsclipping 1918 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence-January-August 1918 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence-August-February 1918-1919 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Dialogues 1917-1919 (Box 9)
  - Copy of The Atlantic Oncely 1918 (Box 9)
  - Photos and post cards 1917-1919 (Box 9)
  - Letter from King George of England to nurses 1918 (Box 9)
  - Travel guide to Nancy, France 1918 (Box 9)
  - Short Stories-Aboard the Adriatic of the White Star Lines, August 1918 (Box 9)
  - Post WWI Christmas Card 1919-1920 (Box 9)
  - Nurses of Base Hospital 45 1932 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence 1910-1919 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1920-1929 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1930 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1931-1932 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence 1933-1934 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1935-1941 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1945-1949 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1950-1959 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence 1975-1976 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Box 11)
- Series II-Literary
  - Titled Short Stories and Narrative Fragments (Box 12)
  - Untitled Short Stories (Box 12)
  - At the Nurses Dining Table (Box 12)
  - A Day on S-4 (Box 12)
  - Do I Sign (Box 12)
  - Dr. Bill (Box 12)
  - Fine Linen (Box 12)
  - A Grain of Sand (Box 12)
  - His Eagle Eye (Box 12)
  - His Handwriting (Box 12)
  - The Junk Dealer (Box 12)
  - The Ladies with Beautiful Hands (Box 12)
  - Low Washing Waves (Box 12)
  - Midnight (Box 12)
  - Mo' lasses (Box 12)
  - Mule Natures, One and Two (Box 12)
  - No Us 'um Arguin' (Box 12)
  - Nurses are like that (Box 12)
  - One Day (Box 12)
  - The Sister (Box 12)
  - Splash of Color on an Old House (Box 12)
  - These Deep Silent Men (Box 12)
  - To Meet the Future (Box 12)
  - Unclassified-A Fool (Box 12)
  - Your Tow Sons (Box 12)
  - Zebidee (Box 12)
  - Essay: A Hundred Years Without Senility (Box 13)
  - Essay: Learning and Living (Box 13)
  - Essay: Notions of a New (Old) Nurse (Box 13)
  - Essay: Not on the Books (Box 13)
  - Essay: Narrative Account of the conference at the Wilson Rehab. Center (Box 13)
  - Essay: Red Cross and the State (Box 13)
  - English Notes (Box 14)
  - English I (Box 14)
  - English III (Box 14)
  - English 130-247 (Box 14)
  - English Class Notes 1927-1928 (Box 14)
  - School Certificate May 31, 1920 (Box 14)
  - Art Class Notes and Clippings (Box 15)
  - Class notes 1931 (Box 15)
  - Class Notes 1930-1931 (Box 15)
  - Class Notes, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Class Notes, n.d. (literature/poetry) (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials 1947-1956 (Box 16)
  - Receipts, bank statements, etc... 1920-1960 (Box 16)
  - Dr. A.A. Houser, December 1926 (Box 16)
  - Poetry by others (Box 16)
  - Drawings, Illustrations, Maps and Photos (Box 16)
  - Periodicals and pamphlets 1925-1976 (Box 16)
  - Newsclippings 1920 (Box 16)